<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>FOF Developer's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><lineage>K.</lineage><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Akeeba Ltd</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>May 2013</pubdate>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license can be found on-line at <link
      xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html</link>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>What is FOF?</title>

      <para><productname>FOF</productname> (Framework on Framework) is a rapid
      application development framework for <trademark>Joomla!</trademark>.
      Unlike other frameworks it is not standalone. It extends the
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> Platform instead of replacing it,
      featuring its own forked and extended version of the MVC classes,
      keeping a strong semblance to the existing
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> MVC API. This means that you don't have
      to relearn writing <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> extensions. Instead,
      you can start being productive from the first day you're using it. Our
      goal is to always support the officially supported LTS versions of
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> and not break backwards compatibility
      without a clear deprecation and migration path.</para>

      <para><productname>FOF</productname> is currently used by Akeeba
      products such as <productname>Akeeba Backup</productname>,
      <productname>Admin Tools</productname>, <productname>Akeeba
      Subscriptions</productname>, <productname>Akeeba Ticket
      System</productname> and <productname>Akeeba DocImport</productname>
      components.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Free Software means collaboration</title>

      <para>The reason of existence of <acronym>FOSS</acronym> (Free and Open
      Source Software) is collaboration between developers.
      <productname>FOF</productname> is no exception; it exists because and
      for the community of <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> developers. It is
      provided free of charge and with all of the freedoms of the GPL for you
      to benefit. And in true Free Software spirit, the community aspect is
      very strong. Participating is easy and fun.</para>

      <para>If you want to discuss <productname>FOF</productname> there is
      <link
      xlink:href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?hl=en&amp;fromgroups#!forum/frameworkonframework">a
      Google Groups mailing list</link>. This is a peer discussion group where
      developers working with <productname>FOF</productname> can freely
      discuss.</para>

      <para>If you have a feature proposal or have found a bug, but you're not
      sure how to code it yourself, please report it on the list.</para>

      <para>If you have a patch feel free to fork <link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/akeeba/fof">this project on GitHub</link>
      (you only need a free account to do that) and send a pull request.
      Please remember to describe what you intended to achieve to help me
      review your code faster.</para>

      <para>If you've found a cool hack (in the benign sense of the word, not
      the malicious one...), something missing from the documentation or have
      a tip which can help other developers feel free to edit the Wiki. We're
      all grown-ups and professionals, I believe there is no need of policing
      the wiki edits. If you're unsure about whether a wiki edit is
      appropriate, please ask on the list.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Preface to this documentation</title>

      <para><productname>FOF</productname> is a rapid application development
      framework for the Joomla! CMS. Instead of trying to completely replace
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark>’s own API (formerly known as the
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> Platform) it builds upon it and extends
      it both in scope and features. In the end of the day it enables
      agony-free extension development for the Joomla! CMS.</para>

      <para>In order to exploit the time-saving capabilities of the
      <productname>FOF</productname> framework to the maximum you need to
      understand how it's organized, the conventions used and how its
      different pieces work together. This documentation attempts to provide
      you with this knowledge.</para>

      <para>As with every piece of documentation we had to answer two big
      questions: where do we start and how do we structure the content. The
      first question was easy to answer. Having given the presentation of the
      <productname>FOF</productname> framework countless times we have
      developed an intuitive grasp of how to start presenting it: from the
      abstract to the concrete.</para>

      <para>The second question was harder to answer. Do we write a dry
      reference to the framework or more of a story-telling documentation
      which builds up its reader’s knowledge? Since we are all developers we
      can read the code (and DocBlocks), meaning that the first option is
      redundant. Therefore we decided to go for the second option.</para>

      <para>As a result this documentation does not attempt to be a complete
      reference, a development gospel, the one and only source of information
      on <productname>FOF</productname>. On the contrary, this documentation
      aims to be the beginning of your journey, much like a travel guide. What
      matters the most is the journey itself, writing your own extensions
      based on <productname>FOF</productname>. As you go on writing software
      you will be full of questions. Most of them you’ll answer yourself. Some
      of them will be already answered in the wiki. A few of them you’ll have
      to ask on the mailing list. In the end of the day you will be richer in
      knowledge. If you do dig up a golden nugget of knowledge, please do
      consider writing a wiki page. This way we’ll all be richer and enjoy our
      coding trip even more.</para>

      <para>Have fun and code on!</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Key features</title>

      <para>Some of the key features / highlights of FOF:</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Convention over configuration, Rails
      style</emphasis>. Instead of having to painstakingly code every single
      bit of your component, it's sufficient to use our naming conventions,
      inspired by Ruby on Rails conventions. For example, if you have
      com_example, the foobar view will read from the #__example_foobars table
      which has a unique key named example_foobar_id. The default
      implementation of controllers, models, tables and views will also cater
      for the majority of use cases, minimising the code you'll need to
      write.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">HMVC today, without relearning component
      development</emphasis>. There's a lot of talk about the need to
      re-engineer the MVC classes in Joomla! to support HMVC. What if we could
      give you HMVC support using the existing MVC classes, today, without
      having to relearn how to write components? Yes, it's possible with FOF.
      It has been possible since September 2011, actually. And for those who
      mumble their words and spread FUD, yes, it IS HMVC by any definition.
      The very existence of the FOFDispatcher class proves the point.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Easy reuse of view template files without
      ugly include()</emphasis>. More often than not you want to reuse view
      template files across views. The "traditional" way was by using
      include() or require() statements. This meant, however, that template
      overrides ceased working. Not any more! Using FOFView's
      loadAnyTemplate() you can load any view template file from the front- or
      back-end of your component or any other component, automatically
      respecting template overrides.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatic language loading and easy
      overrides</emphasis>. Are you sick and tired of having to load your
      component's language files manually? Do you end up with a lot of
      untranslated strings when your translators don't catch up with your new
      features? Yes, that sucks. It's easy to overcome. FOF will automatically
      handle language loading for you.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Media files override (works like template
      overrides)</emphasis>. So far you knew that you can override Joomla!'s
      view template files using template overrides. But what about CSS or
      Javascript files? This usually required the users to "hack core", i.e.
      modify your views' PHP files, ending up in an unmaintainable,
      non-upgradeable and potentially insecure solution. Not any more! Using
      FOF's FOFTemplateUtils::addCSS and FOFTemplateUtils::addJS you can load
      your CSS and JS files directly from the view template file. Even better?
      You can use the equivalent of template overrides to let your users and
      template designers override them with their own implementations. They
      just have to create the directory
      templates/your_template/media/com_example to override the files normally
      found in media/com_example. So easy!</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatic JSON and CSV views with no extra
      code (also useful for web services)</emphasis>. Why struggle to provide
      a remote API for your component? FOF makes the data of each view
      accessible as JSON feeds opening a new world of possibilities for
      Joomla! components (reuse data in mobile apps, Metro-style Windows 8
      tiles, browser extensions, mash-up web applications, ...). The automatic
      CSV views work on the same principle but output data in CSV format,
      suitable for painlessly data importing to spreadsheets for further
      processing. Oh, did we mention that we already have an almost RESTful
      web services implementation?</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">No code view templates</emphasis>. Don't you
      hate it that you have to write a different view template (in PHP and
      HTML) for each Joomla! version and, worse, each template out there?
      Don't you hate it having to teach non-developers how to not screw up
      your component with every update you publish? We feel your pain. That's
      why FOF supports the use of XML files as view templates, rendering them
      automatically to HTML. Not just forms; everything, including browse
      (multiple items) and single item views. Even better, you get to choose
      if you want to use traditional PHP/HTML view templates, XML view
      templates or a combination of both, even in the same view!</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">No code routing, ACL and overall application
      configuration</emphasis>. Since FOF 2.1 you can define your
      application's routing, access control integration and overall
      configuration without routing any code, just by using a simple to
      understand XML file. It's now easier than ever to have Joomla!
      extensions with truly minimal (or no) PHP code.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting started with FOF</title>

      <section>
        <title>Download and install FOF</title>

        <para>You can download FOF as an installable Joomla! library package
        from <link
        xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/download/fof.html">our
        repository</link>. You can install it like any other extension under
        Joomla! 2.x and later.</para>

        <bridgehead>Using the latest development version</bridgehead>

        <para>You can clone a read-only copy of the Git repository of FOF in
        your local machine. Make sure you symlink or copy the fof directory to
        your dev site's libraries/fof directory. Alternatively, we publish dev
        releases in the <link
        xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/download/fof-dev.html">dev
        release repository</link>. These are installable packages but please
        note that they may be out of date compared to the Git HEAD. Dev
        releases are not published automatically and may be several revisions
        behind the current Git master branch.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using it in your extension</title>

        <para>The recommended method for including FOF in your component,
        module or plugin is using this short code snippet right after your
        defined('_JEXEC') or die() statement (Joomla! 2.x and later):</para>

        <programlisting>if (!defined('FOF_INCLUDED')) {
    include_once JPATH_LIBRARIES . '/fof/include.php';
}</programlisting>

        <para>Alternatively, you can use the one-liner:</para>

        <programlisting>require_once JPATH_LIBRARIES . '/fof/include.php';</programlisting>

        <para>From that point onwards you can use FOF in your
        extension.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Installing FOF with your component</title>

        <para>Unfortunately, Joomla! doesn't allow us to version checking
        before installing a library package. This means that it's your
        responsibility to check that there is no newer version of FOF
        installed in the user's site before attempting to install FOF with
        your extension. In the following paragraphs we are going to
        demonstrate one way to do that for Joomla! 2.x / 3.x component
        packages.</para>

        <para>Include a directory called fof in your installation package. The
        directory should contain the files of the installation package's fof
        directory. Then, in your script.mycomponent.php file add the following
        method:</para>

        <programlisting>/**
 * Check if FoF is already installed and install if not
 *
 * @param   object  $parent  class calling this method
 *
 * @return  array            Array with performed actions summary
 */
private function _installFOF($parent)
{
    $src = $parent-&gt;getParent()-&gt;getPath('source');

    // Load dependencies
    JLoader::import('joomla.filesystem.file');
    JLoader::import('joomla.utilities.date');
    $source = $src . '/fof';

    if (!defined('JPATH_LIBRARIES'))
    {
        $target = JPATH_ROOT . '/libraries/fof';
    }
    else
    {
        $target = JPATH_LIBRARIES . '/fof';
    }
    $haveToInstallFOF = false;

    if (!is_dir($target))
    {
        $haveToInstallFOF = true;
    }
    else
    {
        $fofVersion = array();

        if (file_exists($target . '/version.txt'))
        {
            $rawData = JFile::read($target . '/version.txt');
            $info    = explode("\n", $rawData);
            $fofVersion['installed'] = array(
                'version'   =&gt; trim($info[0]),
                'date'      =&gt; new JDate(trim($info[1]))
            );
        }
        else
        {
            $fofVersion['installed'] = array(
                'version'   =&gt; '0.0',
                'date'      =&gt; new JDate('2011-01-01')
            );
        }

        $rawData = JFile::read($source . '/version.txt');
        $info    = explode("\n", $rawData);
        $fofVersion['package'] = array(
            'version'   =&gt; trim($info[0]),
            'date'      =&gt; new JDate(trim($info[1]))
        );

        $haveToInstallFOF = $fofVersion['package']['date']-&gt;toUNIX() &gt; $fofVersion['installed']['date']-&gt;toUNIX();
    }

    $installedFOF = false;

    if ($haveToInstallFOF)
    {
        $versionSource = 'package';
        $installer = new JInstaller;
        $installedFOF = $installer-&gt;install($source);
    }
    else
    {
        $versionSource = 'installed';
    }

    if (!isset($fofVersion))
    {
        $fofVersion = array();

        if (file_exists($target . '/version.txt'))
        {
            $rawData = JFile::read($target . '/version.txt');
            $info    = explode("\n", $rawData);
            $fofVersion['installed'] = array(
                'version'   =&gt; trim($info[0]),
                'date'      =&gt; new JDate(trim($info[1]))
            );
        }
        else
        {
            $fofVersion['installed'] = array(
                'version'   =&gt; '0.0',
                'date'      =&gt; new JDate('2011-01-01')
            );
        }

        $rawData = JFile::read($source . '/version.txt');
        $info    = explode("\n", $rawData);
        $fofVersion['package'] = array(
            'version'   =&gt; trim($info[0]),
            'date'      =&gt; new JDate(trim($info[1]))
        );
        $versionSource = 'installed';
    }

    if (!($fofVersion[$versionSource]['date'] instanceof JDate))
    {
        $fofVersion[$versionSource]['date'] = new JDate;
    }

    return array(
        'required'  =&gt; $haveToInstallFOF,
        'installed' =&gt; $installedFOF,
        'version'   =&gt; $fofVersion[$versionSource]['version'],
        'date'      =&gt; $fofVersion[$versionSource]['date']-&gt;format('Y-m-d'),
    );
}</programlisting>

        <para>You need to call it from inside your postflight() method. For
        example:</para>

        <programlisting>/**
 * Method to run after an install/update/uninstall method
 *
 * @param   object  $type    type of change (install, update or discover_install)
 * @param   object  $parent  class calling this method
 *
 * @return void
 */
function postflight($type, $parent)
{
        $fofInstallationStatus = $this-&gt;_installFOF($parent);
}</programlisting>

        <important>
          <para>Due to a bug/feature in Joomla! 1.6 and later, your
          component's manifest file must start with a letter before L,
          otherwise Joomla! will assume that lib_fof.xml is your extension's
          XML manifest and install FOF instead of your extension. We suggest
          using the com_yourComponentName.xml convention, e.g. com_todo.xml.
          There is a patch pending in Joomla!'s tracker for this issue,
          hopefully it will be accepted sometime soon.</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Sample applications</title>

        <para>FOF comes with two sample applications which are used to
        demonstrate its features, <link
        xlink:href="https://github.com/akeeba/todo-fof-example">To-Do</link>
        and <link xlink:href="https://github.com/akeeba/contactus">Contact
        Us</link>. These were conceived and developed in different points of
        FOF's development. As a result they are always in a state of flux and
        will definitely not expose all of FOF's features.</para>

        <para>Another good way to learn some FOF tricks is by reading the
        source code of existing FOF-based components. Just remember that we
        are all real world developers and sometimes our code is anything but
        kosher ;)</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>The big picture</title>

    <section>
      <title>Overview of a component</title>

      <para>FOF is an MVC framework in heart and soul. It tries to stick as
      close as possible to the MVC conventions put forward by the Joomla! CMS
      since Joomla! 1.5, cutting down on unnecessary code duplication. The
      main premise is that your code will be DRY – not as the opposite of
      “wet”, but as in Don’t Repeat Yourself. Simply put: if you ever find
      yourself trying to copy code from a base class and paste it into a
      specialized class, you are doing it wrong.</para>

      <para>In order to achieve this code isolation, FOF uses a very flexible
      structure for your components. A component's structure looks like
      this:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <info>
          <title>The structure of an FOF-based component</title>
        </info>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/component-structure.png" width="15cm"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The Dispatcher is the entry point of your component. Some people
      would call this a "front Controller" and this is actually what it is.
      It's different than what we typically call a Controller in the sense
      that the Dispatcher is the only part of your component which is supposed
      to interface the underlying application (e.g. the Joomla! CMS) and gets
      to decide which Controller and task to execute based on the input data
      (usually this is the request data). No matter if you call it an entry
      point, front controller, dispatcher or Clint Eastwood its job is to
      figure out what needs to run and run it. We simply chose the name
      "Dispatcher" because, like all conventions, we had to call it something.
      So, basically, the Dispatcher will take a look at the input data, figure
      out which Controller and task to run, create an instance of it, push it
      the data and tell it to run the task. The Controller is expected to
      return the rendered data or a redirection which the Dispatcher will
      dully pass back to its caller.</para>

      <para>Oh, wait, what is a Controller anyway?! Right below the Dispatcher
      you will see a bunch of stuff grouped as a "triad". The "triad" is
      commonly called "view" (with a lowercase v). Each triad does something
      different in your component. For example, one triad may allow you to
      handle clients, another triad allow you to handle orders and so on. Your
      component can have one or more triads. A triad usually contains a
      Controller, a Model and a View, hence the name ("triad" literally means
      "a bunch of three things"). The only mandatory member is the Controller.
      A triad may be reusing the Model and View from another triad – which is
      another reason why DRY code rocks– or it may even be view-less. So, a
      triad may actually be a bunch of one, two or three things, as long as it
      includes a Controller. Just to stop you from being confused or thinking
      about oriental organised crime and generally make your life easier we
      decided to call these "views" (with a lowercase v) instead of "triads".
      See? Now it is so much better.</para>

      <para>FOF views follow the "fat Model - thin Controller" paradigm. This
      means that the Controller is a generally minimalist piece of code and
      the Model is what gets to do all the work. Knowing this very important
      bit of information, let's take a look at the innards of a view.</para>

      <para>In the very beginning we have the Controller. The Controller has
      one or more tasks. Each task is an action of your component, like
      showing a list of records, showing a single record, publish a record,
      delete a record and so on. With a small difference. The Controller's
      tasks do not perform the actual work. They simply spawn an instance of
      the Model and push it the necessary data it needs. This is called
      "setting the state" of the Model. In most cases the Controller will also
      call a Model's method which does something. It's extremely important to
      note that the Controller will work with <emphasis>any</emphasis> Model
      that implements that method and that the Model is oblivious to the
      Controller. Then the Controller will create an instance of the View
      class, pass it the instance of the Model and tell it to go render
      itself. It will take the output of the View and pass it back to the
      Dispatcher.</para>

      <para>Which brings us to the Model. The Model is the workhorse of the
      view. It implements the business logic. All FOF Models are passive
      Models which means that they are oblivious to the presence of the
      Controller and View. Actually, they are completely oblivious to the fact
      that they are part of a triad. That's right, Models can be used
      standalone, outside the context of the view or component they are
      designed to live in. The Model's methods will act upon the state
      variables which have already been set (typically, by the Controller) and
      will only modify the state variables or return the output directly.
      Models must never have to deal with input data directly or talk to
      specific Controllers and/or Views. Models are decoupled from everything,
      that's where their power lies.</para>

      <para>Just a small interlude here. Right below the Model we see a small
      thing called a "Table". This is a strange beast. It's one part data
      adapter, one part model and one part controller, but nothing quite like
      any of this. The Table is used to create an object representing a single
      record. It is typically used to check the validity of a record before
      saving it to the database and post-process a record when reading it from
      the database (e.g. unserialise a field which contains serialised or JSON
      data).</para>

      <para>The final piece of our view is the View class itself. It will ask
      the Model for the raw data and transform it into a suitable
      representation. Typically this means getting the raw records from the
      Model and create the HTML output, but that's not the only use for a
      View. A View could just as well render the data as a JSON stream, a CSV
      file, or even produce a graphic, audio or video file. It's what
      transforms the raw data into something useful, i.e. it's your
      presentation layer. Most often it will do so by loading view templates
      which are .php files which transform raw data to a suitable
      representation. If you are using the XML forms feature of FOF, the View
      will ask the Model to return the form definition and ask FOF's renderer
      to render this to HTML instead. Even though the actual rendering is
      delegated to the Renderer (not depicted above), it's still the View
      that's responsible for the final leg of the rendered data: passing it
      back to its caller. Yes, the View will actually neither output its data
      directly to the browser, nor talk to the underlying application. It
      returns the raw data back to its caller, which is almost always the
      Controller. Again, we have to stress that the View is oblivious to both
      the Controller and the Model being used. A properly written View is
      fully decoupled from everything else and will work with any data
      provider object implementing the same interface as a Model object and a
      caller which is supposed to capture its output for further
      consumption.</para>

      <important>
        <para>All classes comprising a view are fully decoupled. None is aware
        of the internal workings of another object in the same or a different
        view. This allows you to exchange objects at will, promoting code
        reuse. Even though it sounds like a lot of work it's actually less
        work and pays dividends the more features you get to add to your
        components.</para>
      </important>

      <para>There's another bit mentioned below the triad, the Toolbar. The
      Toolbar is something which conceptually belongs to the component and
      only has to do with views being rendered as HTML. It's what renders the
      title in the back-end, the actions toolbar in the front- or back-end and
      the navigation links / menu in the back-end. In case you missed the
      subtle reference: FOFToolbar allows you to render an actions toolbar
      even in the front-end of your component, something that's not possible
      with plain old Joomla!. You will simply need to add some CSS to do
      it.</para>

      <para>Finally we mention the Helpers. The Helpers are pure static
      classes implementing every bit of functionality that's neither OOP, nor
      can it be categorised in any other object already mentioned. For
      example, methods to render drop-down selection lists. In so many words,
      "Helper" is a polite way of saying "non-OOP cruft we'd rather not talk
      about". Keep your Helpers to a minimum as they're a royal pain in the
      rear to test.</para>

      <para>Please do keep in mind that this is just a generic overview of how
      an FOF-based component works. The real power comes from the fact that
      you don't need to know the internal workings of FOF to use it, you don't
      need to copy and paste code from it (woe is the developer who does that)
      and quite possibly you don't even need to write any code. At all. It's
      all discussed later on.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Diving into the FOF classes</title>

      <para>As it was casually mentioned in the previous section, the real
      power of FOF comes from the fact that it doesn't require you to write
      much or any code. All you have to do is to follow some conventions and
      understand what are the default actions carried out by FOF. This
      sections attempts to explain it all, one class at a time.</para>

      <section>
        <title>FOFDispatcher</title>

        <bridgehead>Instantiating and using the Dispatcher</bridgehead>

        <para>Following Joomla conventions, at the root of both the front- and
        back-end of an extension is the entry point for that end of the
        extension, named following the extension’s name.</para>

        <para>For example, for com_foobar, we would create foobar.php in the
        root of each end. These files are not dispatchers, but they are the
        points in the extension that include the FOF library, and create an
        instance of FOF's dispatcher.</para>

        <para>FOF is included with:</para>

        <programlisting>// Load FOF
include_once JPATH_LIBRARIES . '/fof/include.php';
if (!defined('FOF_INCLUDED')) {
    JError::raiseError('500', 'FOF is not installed');
}</programlisting>

        <para>Creating an instance of FOF's dispatcher for com_foobar would be
        done with:</para>

        <programlisting>FOFDispatcher::getTmpInstance('com_foobar')-&gt;dispatch();</programlisting>

        <bridgehead>What FOFDispatcher does</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Convention over Configuration</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Specialising FOFDispatcher</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>FOFDispatcher methods you should know about</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <section>
          <title>Calling a Dispatcher from anywhere (a.k.a. HMVC)</title>

          <para/>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Web services</title>

          <para/>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FOFController</title>

        <bridgehead>What FOFController does</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Convention over Configuration</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Specialising FOFController</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>FOFController methods you should know about</bridgehead>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FOFModel</title>

        <bridgehead>What FOFModel does</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Convention over Configuration</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Specialising FOFModel</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>FOFModel methods you should know about</bridgehead>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FOFTable</title>

        <bridgehead>What FOFTable does</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Convention over Configuration</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Specialising FOFTable</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>FOFTable methods you should know about</bridgehead>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FOFView</title>

        <bridgehead>What FOFView does</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Convention over Configuration</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Specialising FOFView</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>FOFView methods you should know about</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <section>
          <title>FOFView subclasses</title>

          <para/>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>View templates</title>

          <bridgehead>Naming of view template files</bridgehead>

          <para/>

          <bridgehead>Including media files</bridgehead>

          <para/>

          <bridgehead>Reusing view templates</bridgehead>

          <para/>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Template overrides</title>

          <bridgehead>Overriding view templates</bridgehead>

          <para/>

          <bridgehead>Overriding media files</bridgehead>

          <para/>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FOFToolbar</title>

        <bridgehead>What FOFToolbar does</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Convention over Configuration</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>Specialising FOFToolbar</bridgehead>

        <para/>

        <bridgehead>FOFToolbar methods you should know about</bridgehead>

        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>XML Forms</title>

    <para/>

    <section>
      <title>The different form types</title>

      <para/>

      <section>
        <title>Browse forms</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Read forms</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Edit forms</title>

        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Header field types reference</title>

      <para/>

      <section>
        <title>accesslevel</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>field</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>fieldsearchable</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>fieldselectable</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>fieldsql</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>filtersearchable</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>filterselectable</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>filtersql</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>language</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>ordering</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>published</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>rowselect</title>

        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Form field types reference</title>

      <para/>

      <section>
        <title>accesslevel</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>button</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>cachehandler</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>calendar</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>captcha</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>checkbox</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>editor</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>email</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>groupedlist</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>hidden</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>image</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>imagelist</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>integer</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>language</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>list</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>media</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>model</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>ordering</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>password</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>plugins</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>published</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>radio</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>selectrow</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>sessionhandler</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>spacer</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>sql</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>tel</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>text</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>textarea</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>timezone</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>url</title>

        <para/>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>user</title>

        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Configuring the MVC and associated classes</title>

    <para>All MVC and associated classes in FOF (Dispatcher, Controller,
    Model, View, Table, Toolbar) come with a default behavior, for example
    where to look for model files, how to handle request data and so on. While
    this is fine most of the times –as long as you follow FOF’s conventions–
    this is not always desirable.</para>

    <para>For example, if you are building a CCK (something like K2) you may
    want to look for view templates in a non-standard directory in order to
    support alternative “themes”. Or, maybe, if you're building a contact
    component you only want to expose the add view to your front-end users so
    that they can file a contact request but not view other people's contact
    requests. You get the idea.</para>

    <para>The traditional approach to development prescribes overriding
    classes, even to the extent of copying and pasting code. If you've ever
    attended one of my presentations you've probably figured that I consider
    copying and pasting code a mortal sin. You may have also figured that,
    like all developers, I am lazy and dislike writing lots of code.
    Naturally, FOF being a RAD tool it provides an elegant solution to this
    problem. The <code>$config</code> array and its sibling, the
    <filename>fof.xml</filename> file.</para>

    <section>
      <title>What is the <code>$config</code> array?</title>

      <para>You may have observed that FOF’s MVC classes can be passed an
      optional array parameter <code>$config</code>. This is a hash array with
      configuration options. It is being passed from the Dispatcher to the
      Controller and from there to the Model, View and Table classes.
      Essentially, this is your view (MVC triad) configuration. Setting its
      options allows you to modify FOF’s internal workings without writing
      code.</para>

      <para>The various possible settings are explained in “The configuration
      settings” section below.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What’s the deal with the <filename>fof.xml</filename>
      file?</title>

      <para>The <code>$config</code> array is a great idea but has a major
      drawback: you have to create one or several <filename>.php</filename>
      files with specialized classes to use it. Remember the FOF promise about
      not having to write code unless absolutely necessary? Yep, this doesn’t
      stick very well with that promise. So the <filename>fof.xml</filename>
      file was born in FOF 2.1.</para>

      <para>The <filename>fof.xml</filename> file is a simple XML file placed
      inside your component's <emphasis role="bold">back-end</emphasis>
      directory, e.g. <filename>administrator/com_example/fof.xml</filename>.
      It contains configuration overrides for the front-end, back-end and CLI
      parts of your FOF component.</para>

      <section>
        <title>A sample <filename>fof.xml</filename> file</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;fof&gt;
	&lt;!-- Component back-end options --&gt;
	&lt;backend&gt;
		&lt;!-- Dispatcher options --&gt;
		&lt;dispatcher&gt;
			&lt;option name="default_view"&gt;items&lt;/option&gt;
		&lt;/dispatcher&gt;
	&lt;/backend&gt;
	
	&lt;!-- Component front-end options --&gt;
	&lt;frontend&gt;
		&lt;!-- Dispatcher options --&gt;
		&lt;dispatcher&gt;
			&lt;option name="default_view"&gt;item&lt;/option&gt;
		&lt;/dispatcher&gt;
		&lt;!-- Options common for all views --&gt;
		&lt;view name="*"&gt;
			&lt;!-- Per-task ACL settings. The star task sets the default ACL privileges for all tasks. --&gt;
			&lt;acl&gt;
				&lt;task name="*"&gt;false&lt;/task&gt;
			&lt;/acl&gt;
		&lt;/view&gt;
		&lt;view name="item"&gt;
			&lt;!-- Task mapping --&gt;
			&lt;taskmap&gt;
				&lt;task name="list"&gt;browse&lt;/task&gt;
			&lt;/taskmap&gt;
			&lt;!-- Per-task ACL settings. An empty string removes ACL checks. --&gt;
			&lt;acl&gt;
				&lt;!-- Everyone, including guests, can access dosomething --&gt;
				&lt;task name="dosomething"&gt;&lt;/task&gt;
				&lt;!-- Only people with the core.manage privilege can access the somethingelse task --&gt;
				&lt;task name="somethingelse"&gt;core.manage&lt;/task&gt;
			&lt;/acl&gt;
		&lt;/view&gt;
	&lt;/frontend&gt;
&lt;/fof&gt;
</programlisting>

        <para>The <filename>fof.xml</filename> file has an
        <code>&lt;fof&gt;</code> root element. Inside it you can have zero or
        one tags called <code>&lt;frontend&gt;</code>,
        <code>&lt;backend&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;cli&gt;</code> which
        configure FOF for front-end, back-end and CLI access respectively.
        Please note that the CLI is a special case: it will mix both the
        back-end and CLI settings to derive the final configuration. In the
        other two cases (front- or back-end access) only the configuration for
        this specific mode of access will be used.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Dispatcher settings</title>

        <para>You can configure the way the Dispatcher works using the
        <code>&lt;dispatcher&gt;</code> tag. Inside it you can have one or
        more <code>&lt;option&gt;</code> tags. The name attribute defines the
        name of the configuration variable to set, while the tag's content
        defines the value of this configuration variable.</para>

        <para>The available variables are:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>default_view</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Defines the default view to show if none is defined in the
              input data. By default this is <option>cpanel</option>. In the
              example above we set it to items in the back-end and item in the
              front-end.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>View settings</title>

        <para>There are several options that are applied per view. In the
        context of the <filename>fof.xml</filename> file, a “view” actually
        refers to an MVC triad, not just the View part of the triad. In so
        many words, the options affect the Controller, Model and View used to
        render this particular component view. You define the view the options
        apply to using the <code>name</code> attribute of the view tag.</para>

        <para>The settings of each view are isolated from the settings of
        every other view, with one notable exception: the star view, i.e.
        <code>name="*"</code>. This is a placeholder view that defines the
        default settings. These settings are applied to all views. If you also
        have a view tag for a view, the default settings (from the star view)
        and the settings for the particular view are merged together. This
        applies to all settings described below.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Task map settings</title>

          <para>The task map settings allow you to map specific tasks to
          specific Controller methods. Other frameworks would call this the
          “routing” feature. It works the same way as adding running
          <code>registerTask</code> in your specialized Controller
          class.</para>

          <para>The task map is enclosed inside a single
          <code>&lt;taskmap&gt;</code> tag. You can have exactly zero or one
          <code>&lt;taskmap&gt;</code> tags inside each view tag.</para>

          <para>Inside the <code>&lt;taskmap&gt;</code> tag you can have one
          or more <code>&lt;task&gt;</code> tags. The <code>name</code>
          attribute defines the name of the task to map, whereas the content
          of the tag defines the controller’s method which will be called for
          this task.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>ACL settings</title>

          <para>The ACL settings can be used to override or fine-tune the
          access control for each task of the particular view. Even though FOF
          comes with default ACL mappings for its basic tasks, these are not
          always sufficient or appropriate for all situations. Normally this
          is achieved by overriding the
          <code>onBefore<replaceable>Taskname</replaceable></code> methods in
          the Controller, e.g. <code>onBeforeSave</code> to set up the ACL
          checks for the save task. You can use the ACL mappings in the
          <filename>fof.xml</filename> instead of such checks. You can even
          use the ACL mapping in <filename>fof.xml</filename> for custom tasks
          for which no
          <code>onBefore<replaceable>Taskname</replaceable></code> method
          exists.</para>

          <para>The ACL settings are enclosed inside a single
          <code>&lt;acl&gt;</code> tag. You can have exactly zero or one
          <code>&lt;acl&gt;</code> tags inside each view tag.</para>

          <para>Inside the <code>&lt;acl&gt;</code> tag you can have one or
          more <code>&lt;task&gt;</code> tags. The name attribute defines the
          name of the task to apply the access control, whereas the content of
          the tag defines the Joomla! ACL privilege required to access this
          task. You can use any core ACL privilege or any custom ACL privilege
          defined in your component's <filename>access.xml</filename> file. If
          you leave the content blank then no ACL check is performed (the task
          is always accessible by all users). If you use the special value
          false then the ACL privilege is always going to fail, i.e. the task
          will not be accessible by any user.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Option settings</title>

          <para>The <code>&lt;option&gt;</code> tag can be used to set up a
          setting of this View. It is equivalent to passing a value in the
          <code>$config</code> array. The <code>name</code> attribute defines
          the name of the configuration setting you want to modify. The
          content of the tag is the value of this setting.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The configuration settings</title>

      <para>The following settings can be used either in the
      <code>$config</code> array passed to a Dispatcher, Controller, Model or
      View class or in the <filename>fof.xml</filename> file’s
      <code>&lt;option&gt;</code> tags inside the <code>&lt;view&gt;</code>
      tags.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>autoRouting</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A bit mask which defines the automatic URL routing of
            redirections. A value of 1 means that front-end redirections will
            be put through Joomla!’s JRoute::_(). A value of 2 means that
            back-end redirections will be put through Joomla!’s JRoute::_().
            You can combine multiple values by adding them together.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>base_path</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The base path of the component.</para>

            <para>In $config: Specify the absolute path.</para>

            <para>In fof.xml: Specify a path relative to the site’s
            root.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>cacheableTasks</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A comma separated list of tasks which support Joomla!’s
            caching.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>cid</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Define a comma separated list of item IDs to limit the view
            on. Normally this is empty. Only use when you want to limit a view
            to very specific items. Only valid in the
            <filename>fof.xml</filename> file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>csrf_protection</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Should we be doing a token check for the tasks of this view?
            The possible values are:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>0 - no token checks are performed</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>1 - token checks are always performed</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>2 - token checks are always performed in the back-end
                and in in the front-end, but only when the request format is
                'html' (default setting)</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>3 - token checks are performer only in the
                back-end</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>default_task</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The task to execute if none is defined. The default value is
            <option>display</option>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>event_after_delete</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The content plugin event to trigger after deleting the data.
            Default: onContentAfterDelete</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>event_after_save</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The content plugin event to trigger after saving the data.
            Default: onContentAfterSave</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>event_before_delete</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The content plugin event to trigger before deleting the
            data. Default: onContentBeforeDelete</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>event_before_save</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The content plugin event to trigger before saving the data.
            Default: onContentBeforeSave</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>event_change_state</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The content plugin event to trigger after changing the
            published state of the data. Default: onContentChangeState</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>event_clean_cache</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The content plugin event to trigger when cleaning cache.
            There is no default value.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>helper_path</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The path where the View will be looking for helper classes.
            By default it's the <filename>helpers</filename> directory inside
            your component's directory.</para>

            <para>In $config: Specify an absolute path.</para>

            <para>In fof.xml: Specify a path relative to the component's
            directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>id</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Define an item ID to limit the view on. Normally this is
            empty. Only use when you want to limit a view to one single item.
            Only valid in the <filename>fof.xml</filename> file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>ignore_request</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set to 1 to prevent the Model's populateState() method from
            running. By default the method is empty and does nothing, as the
            Model is supposed to be decoupled from the request information,
            having the Controller push state variables to it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>layout</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The default layout to use for this view. This is normally
            determined automatically based on the task currently being
            executed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>model_path</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The path where the Controller will be looking for Model
            class files. By default it's the <filename>models</filename>
            directory of the component's directory.</para>

            <para>In $config: Specify an absolute path.</para>

            <para>In fof.xml: Specify a path relative to the component's
            directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>model_prefix</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The naming prefix for the Model to be loaded by the
            Controller. The default option is
            <code><replaceable>Componentname</replaceable>Model</code> where
            <replaceable>Componentname</replaceable> is the name of the
            component without the com_ prefix.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>modelName</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the Model class to load. Automatically defined
            based on the component and view names.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>searchpath</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The path where Controller classes will be searched for. By
            default it's the <filename>controllers</filename> directory inside
            your component's directory.</para>

            <para>In $config: Specify the absolute path.</para>

            <para>In fof.xml: Specify a path relative to the component's root
            directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>table_path</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The path where the Model will be looking for table classes.
            By default it's the <filename>tables</filename> directory inside
            your component's directory.</para>

            <para>In $config: Specify an absolute path.</para>

            <para>In fof.xml: Specify a path relative to the component's
            directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>table</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set the name of the table class the Model will use. Please
            note that the the component name is added to this name
            automatically. For example, given a component com_example and a
            table setting of <option>foobar</option> the actual table class
            which will be used will be <code>ExampleTableFoobar</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>tbl</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the database table to use in the table class of
            this view. It is in the format of
            <database>#__tablename</database>, e.g. #__example_items</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>tbl_key</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the key field of the database table to use in
            the table class of this view. It is in the format of
            component_view_id, e.g. example_item_id.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>template_path</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The path where the View will be looking for view template
            (.php) or form (.xml) files. By default it's the
            <filename>tmpl</filename> directory inside the current view's
            directory.</para>

            <para>In $config: Specify an absolute path.</para>

            <para>In fof.xml: Specify a path relative to the component's
            directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>view_path</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The path where the Controller will be looking for View class
            files. By default it's the <filename>views</filename> directory
            inside your component's directory.</para>

            <para>In $config: Specify an absolute path.</para>

            <para>In fof.xml: Specify a path relative to the component's
            directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>viewName</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the View class to load. Automatically defined
            based on the component and view names.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <appendix version="5.0" xml:id="gnu-fdl">
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

    <para>Copyright (C) 2000, 2001, 2002 Free Software Foundation,
    <abbrev>Inc.</abbrev> 51 Franklin <abbrev>St</abbrev> , Fifth Floor,
    Boston, <abbrev>MA</abbrev> 02110-1301 <abbrev
    role="initialism">USA</abbrev> . Everyone is permitted to copy and
    distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but changing it is
    not allowed.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">0. PREAMBLE</bridgehead>

    <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other
    functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to assure
    everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or
    without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily,
    this License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit
    for their work, while not being considered responsible for modifications
    made by others.</para>

    <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative
    works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It
    complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license
    designed for free software.</para>

    <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
    free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
    program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
    software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it can
    be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or whether it
    is published as a printed book. We recommend this License principally for
    works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</bridgehead>

    <para>This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium,
    that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a
    world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work
    under the conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers to any
    such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is
    addressed as "you". You accept the license if you copy, modify or
    distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright
    law.</para>

    <para>A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the
    Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with modifications
    and/or translated into another language.</para>

    <para>A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section
    of the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the
    publishers or authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject
    (or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly
    within that overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook
    of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.) The
    relationship could be a matter of historical connection with the subject
    or with related matters, or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical
    or political position regarding them.</para>

    <para>The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles
    are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice that
    says that the Document is released under this License. If a section does
    not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be
    designated as Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections.
    If the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then there are
    none.</para>

    <para>The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are
    listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says
    that the Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may
    be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.</para>

    <para>A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy,
    represented in a format whose specification is available to the general
    public, that is suitable for revising the document straightforwardly with
    generic text editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint
    programs or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
    is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a
    variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters. A copy made in
    an otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of markup,
    has been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent modification by
    readers is not Transparent. An image format is not Transparent if used for
    any substantial amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called
    "Opaque".</para>

    <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
    ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or
    XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
    PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent
    image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary
    formats that can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors,
    SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by
    some word processors for output purposes only.</para>

    <para>The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself,
    plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material
    this License requires to appear in the title page. For works in formats
    which do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near
    the most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning
    of the body of the text.</para>

    <para>A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose
    title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following
    text that translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands for a
    specific section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements",
    "Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of
    such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
    section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.</para>

    <para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice
    which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty
    Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
    but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
    these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
    meaning of this License.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">2. VERBATIM COPYING</bridgehead>

    <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
    commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the copyright
    notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to the
    Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
    conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use technical
    measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying of the
    copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept compensation in
    exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</para>

    <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above,
    and you may publicly display copies.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">3. COPYING IN QUANTITY</bridgehead>

    <para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have
    printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
    Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
    copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
    Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
    cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
    publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title
    with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
    other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited to
    the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and satisfy
    these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
    respects.</para>

    <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
    legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably)
    on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.</para>

    <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering
    more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent copy
    along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a
    computer-network location from which the general network-using public has
    access to download using public-standard network protocols a complete
    Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material. If you use the
    latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you begin
    distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent
    copy will remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one
    year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or
    through your agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

    <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of
    the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to
    give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
    Document.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">4. MODIFICATIONS</bridgehead>

    <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under
    the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release the
    Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified Version
    filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and
    modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In
    addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title
        distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous
        versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History
        section of the Document). You may use the same title as a previous
        version if the original publisher of that version gives
        permission.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or
        entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the
        Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal authors
        of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than
        five), unless they release you from this requirement.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
        Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
        adjacent to the other copyright notices.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license
        notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under
        the terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum
        below.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant
        Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license
        notice.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title,
        and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors,
        and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If
        there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document, create one
        stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as
        given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
        Version as stated in the previous sentence.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document
        for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise
        the network locations given in the Document for previous versions it
        was based on. These may be placed in the "History" section. You may
        omit a network location for a work that was published at least four
        years before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of the
        version it refers to gives permission.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications",
        Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the
        substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or
        dedications given therein.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
        unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the
        equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section
        may not be included in the Modified Version.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
        "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant
        Section.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
    appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
    copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all of
    these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of
    Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice. These titles
    must be distinct from any other section titles.</para>

    <para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains
    nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various parties--for
    example, statements of peer review or that the text has been approved by
    an organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.</para>

    <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and
    a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list
    of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of Front-Cover
    Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements
    made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a cover text for
    the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same
    entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
    replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher
    that added the old one.</para>

    <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
    License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert
    or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

    <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released under
    this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified
    versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the
    Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list
    them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license
    notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.</para>

    <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
    multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy.
    If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different
    contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end
    of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of
    that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment
    to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license
    notice of the combined work.</para>

    <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History"
    in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled "History";
    likewise combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements", and any
    sections Entitled "Dedications". You must delete all sections Entitled
    "Endorsements".</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

    <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
    documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies
    of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is
    included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this
    License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other
    respects.</para>

    <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
    distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy
    of this License into the extracted document, and follow this License in
    all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT
    WORKS</bridgehead>

    <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate
    and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or
    distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright resulting
    from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of the
    compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit. When the
    Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the
    other works in the aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of
    the Document.</para>

    <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
    copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the
    entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers that
    bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of
    covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear
    on printed covers that bracket the whole aggregate.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">8. TRANSLATION</bridgehead>

    <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
    Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission
    from their copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or
    all Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these
    Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this License, and all
    the license notices in the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers,
    provided that you also include the original English version of this
    License and the original versions of those notices and disclaimers. In
    case of a disagreement between the translation and the original version of
    this License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will
    prevail.</para>

    <para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
    "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its
    Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual title.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">9. TERMINATION</bridgehead>

    <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document
    except as expressly provided for under this License. Any other attempt to
    copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
    automatically terminate your rights under this License. However, parties
    who have received copies, or rights, from you under this License will not
    have their licenses terminated so long as such parties remain in full
    compliance.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS
    LICENSE</bridgehead>

    <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of
    the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
    will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail
    to address new problems or concerns. See <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/">
    http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</link> .</para>

    <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
    number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of
    this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option of
    following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or of
    any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free
    Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version number of
    this License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft)
    by the Free Software Foundation.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1">ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your
    documents</bridgehead>

    <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy
    of the License in the document and put the following copyright and license
    notices just after the title page:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Copyright (C) YEAR YOUR NAME.</para>

      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover
    Texts, replace the "with...Texts." line with this:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
      Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being
      LIST.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
    combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
    situation.</para>

    <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
    recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
    software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their
    use in free software.</para>
  </appendix>
</book>
